Feiss Company Records 5614
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Feiss Company Records
1905-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Feiss Company
5614
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Patents, records (documents).
This collection is made up of letters, notes, articles, and other papers pertaining to the life and career of Richard A. Feiss.
2297063
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 02, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
After receiving a law degree from Harvard, Feiss joined his father's clothing manufacturing business, where he attempted to combine elements of Frederick Taylor's theories of scientific management with his own theories of personal relationship. His goal was to establish a factory in which production was efficient while at the same time the employees had the opportunity to experience personal development, growth, and self actualization.
To improve production, Feiss employed aspects of scientific management, including standardization of equipment, routing instructions, and time studies. To enhance conditions for the workers, he established a program of "Personal Relationships" which gave the workers a chance to participate in decision-making, and also improved the selection, orientation processes. Additionally, workers were offered counseling services, recreational facilities, mental and physical examinations, and other advantages.
Due to economic hardships and personality conflicts among the top managers in Joseph & Feiss, R.A. Feiss resigned from the company in 1925 and went into business on his own. Consequently, the system he developed at Clothcraft crumbled.
Scope and Contents
The collection consist primarily of notes and articles on work standardization and personnel policies, and routine business materials used in industrial organizations practicing scientific management principles. The collection reflects Feiss' work and theories on worker welfare and personal relationships, as influenced by Frederick W. Taylor's scientific management principles.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I. R.A. Feiss.. Professional Papers
Series II. Richard A. Feiss. Articles, Speeches, Papers
Series III. Joseph & Feiss & Co. Papers
Series IV. R.A. Feiss, Inc.
Clothing workers. United States. Health and hygiene.; Labor and laboring classes. Mental health. United States.; Men's clothing industry. United States. Management.; Scientific management.; Wages. Men's clothing industry. United States.; Abt, Jacob.; Feiss, Richard A. (Richard Albert), 1878-1954; Getasky, I. M.; Stillman, William O.; Taylor, Frederick Winslow, 1856-1915; Joseph and Feiss Company (Cleveland, Ohio); R.A. Feiss Company; Tabor Manufacturing Company; United States. National War Labor Board (1918-1919); United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945)
2297063
- Series I. R.A. Feiss.. Professional Papers
  - Correspondence re disaffiliation with Joseph & Feiss Co., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1-1b)
    Scope and Contents
    and personal with R.A.F.'s father re post Feiss Co. career; correspondence. re Manufacturing Laboratories, Inc
  - Correspondence, General, 1915-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    includes Feiss-Dryfoos Genealogy
  - Correspondence with Professor Henry H. Farquhar and Farquhar's letters and activities at Harvard Business School, 1920-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Correspondence with Carl Barth, 1914-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  - Correspondence with William 0. Stillman concerning post J & F Co. Career plans, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence re "On The Problem of Organizing for the Chief Executive", 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
    includes form letters, articles, pamphlets, by Committee for Constitutional Government
  - Employment Forms (Applications, etc.), 1928-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Forms & Publications for Ordnance Division, U.S. Armed Forces, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
  - Memoranda-Joseph & Feiss Co., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes appraisal of economic problems and policy
  - Needle Trades Conference of America (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    Correspondence, 9/18-2/19
  - Needle Trades Conference of America, Reports and Constitution, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    1918 Needle Trades Conference of America. Notes from 1918 meeting
  - Notes on the operating of the Bedaux System (Box 2, Folder 3)
    no date
  - Notes from Courses taught at University of California, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Patent, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Price slips for piece work, includes transparencies
  - Tabor Manufacturing Material, 1905-1915 (Box 2, Folder 8-19)
    plus no date; Philadelphia, PA.-includes work orders, foundry tags, pay differentials, tool lists, instructions, bills, requisitions
  - Miscellaneous, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    paper on filing system by subjects and coding symbols; instructions, logic, examples, n.d., plus "The Place of the College in Collecting and Conserving the Data of Scientific Management" by W. Lewis, 1912
  - Partial list of books referring to Feiss' work (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series II. Richard A. Feiss. Articles, Speeches, Papers
  - Miscellaneous articles from Factory and The Magazine of Management, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Scientific Management Applied to the Steadying of Employment, and Its Effect In An Industrial Establishment", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    May-15
  - "Personal Relationship As A Basis of Scientific Management", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    1915 and a 1924 reprint, 15 pp
  - "Personal Relationship in Business Administration", 1916 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Spirit of Scientific Management," "Maximum vs. Minimus Hour Legislation", 1917 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Stimulating Labor Efficiency in Wartime", 1918 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "A National Labor Policy," (address), 1919 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "The Engineering Approach to the Problem of Continuous Employment", 1921 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Scientific Management During Times of Depression" (address), 1922 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 10 "The Life of Frederick W. Taylor, A Review", 1924 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Mental Hygiene for the Management", 1927 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    1927 and a 1928 reprint
  - "Scientific Management Methods As Applied to A Manufacturing Organization", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    124 pp
  - "On the Problem of Organizing for the Chief Executive", 1943 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Past, Present and Future", 1924 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series III. Joseph & Feiss & Co. Papers
  - Accounting and Bookkeeping Forms (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Articles of Agreement, 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Stock/Shareholders- Agreement, R.A. Feiss, et. al. - Owners
  - Amendment to 1920 Articles of Agreement, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Owners stockholdings agreement
  - Articles on Company, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Emma Britten-Welfare Dept. in J & F
  - Article on Company, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    "Lizzie Likes Her Job"
  - Article on Company, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    "Experiment and Statistics in the Selection of Employees"
  - Balance of Stores & Stock Keeping Forms (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Budget and Operating Costs, Statement, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Classification of Departmental Charges, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Comparative Costs, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Condensed Balance sheet, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Employment and service department: Mary Gibson, articles, 1918-1977 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Expense operating statement, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Financial statements, 1932-1953 (Box 4, Folder 19-32)
  - Income and expense statement, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Instructions for handling orders (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
  - Interdepartmental memorandum, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    "Employee Representation In Industry," p. 44-49, Material on J & F Co
  - Memorandum forms, personal, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Photo (Xerox) of Julius Feiss, Co-founder, Joseph & Feiss Co., The Cleveland Press, July 14, 1953, p. 23
  - Notice of Stockholders Meeting, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 100th Anniversary Banquet, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Clippings, Program (which includes history of company)
  - Order Forms (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Organization Charts, 1925-1928 (Box 5, Folder 4a)
  - Personnel Forms (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
    n.d. (Includes pension booklet, work forms, medical and dental records)
  - Record Forms, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
    n.d. (Includes payroll form)
  - Report to the Board of Directors, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Routing Instructions, 1918-1920 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Superintendent of Planning, Keppele Hall Articles, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Wage Systems; Planning Department Instrument of Executive Control
  - Superintendent of Planning, Keppele Hall Budget Notes, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Superintendent of Planning, Keppele Hall, Period Average Cost Report, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Time Study For Rate Setting, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Time Study "Make-Up Ready" Form (Box 5, Folder 18)
    n.d. (for sewing trousers)
  - Visitors Book, 1910-1925 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Includes Signatures of Frederick Taylor and Frank Gilbreth
  - Photographs-Clothcraft, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    R.A. Feiss; Feiss Plant; Carl Barth and Miscellaneous photos
- Series IV. R.A. Feiss, Inc.
  - Detail Analysis of Expense Forms (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Forms (Box 6, Folder 3)
    n.d. (Balance of Stores, Operating Forecast)
  - Operating Forecast, Statement, Forms (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Organization Chart, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlet on Lewis: "The Perfect Blind Stitch Machine" (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Scientific Management As Applied to a Manufacturing Organization", 1928 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Draft
  - Procurement of Materials, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Procurement of Manufactured Product (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Procurement of Materials or Supplies from Store Room (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Production of Product (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Procurement of Product from Factory (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Procurement of Product from Customer (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Distribution of Expenditures (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Announcement of R.A. Feiss, Inc, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    consulting service and promotional material (photocopies)
  - Herman Hutkin Data, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    correspondence
  - Correspondence with Mrs. Richard Feiss, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 17)